<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Home</title>
    <link>/project/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Home</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/project/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Owens Illinoise Student Case Competition</title>
      <link>/project/owens-illinoise-student-case-competition/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/owens-illinoise-student-case-competition/</guid>
      <description>&lt;style&gt;
body {
text-align: justify}
&lt;/style&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our team (Me, Alex Frank and Yanan Tang) were declared runners up at the Owen Illinois Student Case competition. Although we are sad we couldn&amp;rsquo;t win (even though we probably deserved it) we are delighted that our hard work paid off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pallavr/Owen-Illinois-Competition&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;link&lt;/a&gt; to the github page where you can access the final results. We used state of the art univariate forecasting techniques such as ETS, traditional forecasting techniques such as ARIMA and Time Series Regression and also simple forecasting techniques such as seasonal naive model to forecast the future sales volume of the product line of Owens Illinois.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those who don&amp;rsquo;t know, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.o-i.com/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Owens Illinois&lt;/a&gt; is one of the largest glass manufacturing firms in the United States. We are extremely lucky to have had the opportunity to analyze a large data set in R. The dimension of the data set made the project more challenging. We had to forcast for several products (about five) for each country using five different models. The experience was fascinating because personally, I was able to get first hand insight into what a large data set looks like and then execute a plan to finish the project. It was a huge learning curve for me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I certainly look forward to many more challenges in the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
