<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on Home</title>
    <link>/publication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on Home</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2018</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/publication/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>A Framework for Estimating Customer Worth Under Competing Risk</title>
      <link>/publication/a-framework-for-estimating-customer-worth-under-competing-risk/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/a-framework-for-estimating-customer-worth-under-competing-risk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;style&gt;
body {
text-align: justify}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a sneak peak into my current working paper. Our research has potential in business settings where customers face multiple causes of churn.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt; Pallav Routh, Dr. Jeff Meyer,Dr. Arkajyoti Roy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the presence of multiple causes of exit, a customer’s survival propensity due to a specific cause is affected by all other competing causes of churn. Consequently, the worth of a customer within such a firm would also be affected by these competing forces. Therefore, the lifetime value for such customers must incorporate this competing information. In this paper, we implement a Competing Risk model for estimating the worth of a customer who faces simultaneous risks of temporary or permanent disengagement of membership from the firm. To overcome the limitations of traditional semi-parametric modeling approaches we implement a Random Survival Forest model to predict the survival probability of customer influenced by competing causes of churn. In doing so, we extend the literature on prediction of survival probabilities beyond non-competing scenarios. By the same token, we also extend the literature on customer relationship valuation under contractual business settings in the presence of multiple causes of churn. We demonstrate analytical insights that (i) investigate factors that contribute to a specific cause of churn (ii) reflect the trade-offs between predicted risk and customer value (iii) segment the predicted customer valuation curves over time (iv) study the behavior of predictor variables within such segments. Finally we utilize the prediction and analytical results to optimize the marketing-budget allocation within these customer valuation segments thereby bridging the gap between predictive and prescriptive analytics.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Subjectivity to Objectivity: Measuring Customer Lifetime Value Constructs</title>
      <link>/publication/from-subjectivity-to-objectivity-measuring-customer-lifetime-value-constructs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/from-subjectivity-to-objectivity-measuring-customer-lifetime-value-constructs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;style&gt;
body {
text-align: justify}
&lt;/style&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This post is about my first publication in a local journal on outlining the contributions of Customer Lifetime Value (CLV) to marketing within a firm. Customer Lifetime Value is where my infatuation towards data science and likeness towards data science all began. I didn’t even know about CLV until I was asked to present on it in my marketing strategy class by my professor, Dr. Banerjee. That lead me to an article called “Modeling Customer Lifetime Value” by Gupta et al (2006). That article had opened my eyes to a fascinating world of quantitative marketing and customer relationship management (CRM).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Overview&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a link to my &lt;a href=&#34;http://citeseerx.ist.psu.edu/viewdoc/download?doi=10.1.1.741.7971&amp;amp;rep=rep1&amp;amp;type=pdf&#34;&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;. It gives a gentle introduction to how CLV fits into the marketing machinery. Then the article focuses on the issue of balancing acquisition and retention expenses and how CLV easily helps to address the issue. I even go on to prove this with a hypothetical example that shows how CLV, even in its most simplest form, can capture the problem of balancing cost and guide managers in decision making. This is just one of the several uses of CLV as a marketing metric. CLV has evolved tremendously evolved over the years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Authors&lt;/strong&gt; Dr. Shivaji Banerjee, Pallav Routh&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As data drives decision making in business more and more, it becomes essential to objectify key market metrics such as Customer Lifetime Value (CLV). CLV is the value added by a customer to a firm’s profits during its association with the firm’s products or services. Therefore it becomes important for firms to employ suitable strategies to prolong a customer’s lifetime. In this paper we have taken this subjective aspect of CLV and given it a measurement. We have used this measurement to establish a connection between customer satisfaction and maximization of ROI. Next we have again used this measurement to compare three different marketing strategies in a market driven firm.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
